#### GEOFFREY K. BWAKALI

Email: gkachi2005@yahoo.com OR kachibwakali@gmail.com

Cell phone: +254722125639

## PO BOX 147, MUMIAS,

A graduate in food science with post graduate degree in Business Administration n (strategic Management) and vast experience in the manufacturing sector which includes tea, sugar and corn wet milling industry spurning for over sixteen years. I have thorough knowledge of quality assurance, quality control, ISO and regulatory standards which include 9001, 14001, 45001,17021-1-2015 and 22000 series (both FSMS and FSSC), Fairtrade and Rainforest Alliance. I have been honoured with certificate of excellence in quality management by the World Confederation of businesses held in Malaysia November 2019. I am a member of the National Quality Institute – KEBS/NQI/M/PER/431, and Kenya Institute of Management-KIM-MSDM-63999.

### **Professional Experience**

# **Assistant Manager-Quality Assurance**

June 2017 - Present

Chai Trading Company (www.chaitrading.com), Mombasa (Kenya) (Subsidiary of Kenya Tea development agency)

This organization deals with tea warehousing, fertilizer operations tea blending tea trading and freight and logistics based in Mombasa.

### **Duties and Responsibilities**

- Sound product (both tea and fertilizer) stewardship during warehousing, transportation and shipment process through established inspection regimes.
- Risk management as key risk champion. This include operational risks: safety, environmental and product safety related.
- Developing SOPs and work instructions in liaison with process owners for seamless operations.
- Ensuring effective execution of all audits 1st, 2nd and 3rd party audits.
- Ensuring adherence to OSH act through periodic inspections, reporting and employee involvement through meetings.
- Ensuring certification for ISO and other standards including Fairtrade, GMP, USFDA and Rainforest alliance by handling successful process and system audits.
- Ensuring effective implementation of the system across all Chai Trading Company Limited operations.
- Matching infrastructure and system requirements.

- Ensure adequate training for all process owners on system requirements and maintenance.
- Ensure clear link between systems performances and overall customer satisfaction.
- Ensure compliance to other statutory and regulatory systems requirements on product quality, environment and safety.
- Liaison with statutory and regulatory bodies including NEMA, KEBS, AFA/TBK, KEPHIS, County government public health, and certification bodies.
- Facilitating training of teams and workforces on quality, safety and food safety objectives, lead and motivate teams of workforces by communicating and reinforcing expected standards of performance.
- Developing a quality assurance inspection and controlling program and communicating to all respective process owners.
- Designing processes in conformance with systems.
- Advising management on capital investments based on quality systems requirements.
- Take responsibility for Non-conformances / CARs from Audit reports.
- Ensure traceability and recall for all products; ensuring non-conforming goods are identified, isolated and placed on hold to undergo due process.
- Investigates complaints on existing products and services and works with respective functions to close.
- Develops and recommends test procedures for products and packaging materials and liaising outsourced laboratories for testing, conducting and reporting statistical analysis and trend charts.
- Managing equipment calibrations.

#### Warehouse Officer

June 2016 - June 2017

Chai Trading Company (www.chaitrading.com), Mombasa (Kenya)

# **Duties and Responsibilities**

- Supervise the receipt, dispatching, and storage of goods. (Tea and fertilizer)
- Managing warehouse staff, and other equipment, and oversee security, sanitation, and administrative functions within the warehouse.
- Proper inventory control through monthly stock taking.

Chai Trading Company (www.chaitrading.com), Mombasa (Kenya)

## **Duties and Responsibilities**

The duties are as detailed in the Assistant Manager Quality Assurance post above.

This is after a job re-evaluation exercise that necessitated change of title and reporting structure.

### **Assistant Quality Assurance Manager**

February 2010 - February 2012

Corn products Kenya Limited, Eldoret (Kenya)

This organization currently Ingredion International deals with corn refinery the derivatives being

Starch, glucose syrup, maize germ, dextrin and animal feeds.

## **Duties and Responsibilities: -**

- Product development which included working with our juice manufacturing clients to develop juices with glucose syrup as an alternate sweetener to the artificial sweeteners. This was a better product considering glucose is good nutrition n alternative compared to refined sugars.
- Overseen team of 15 analysts to churn out timely and accurate results in guiding the process controls through proficiency and repeatability tests.
- Assumed the full responsibilities of quality assurance manager in his absence.
- Developed and implemented quality plan.
- Participated in hygiene, safety and quality audits of the plant to identify gaps therein and narrow them.
- Performed quality management system audits in the plant to comply with the statutory requirements.
- Carried out performance appraisal of my subordinates.
- Handled customer quality related complaints by establishing root cause analysis to avoid future recurrence.
- Handled pest control regimes in the plant.
- Part of the food safety management system team.
- Product release to market by issuing certificate of compliance.
- Taken part in employee disciplinary procedures in case of anomalies.
- Ensured work is done within budget by reducing the running costs.

### Company Microbiologist

### March 2004 - February 2010

Corn Products Kenya Limited, Eldoret (Kenya)

### **Duties and Responsibilities: -**

- Microbiological analysis of finished products, process intermediates and water supply to ensure compliance
- Plant hygiene audits and circulating the housekeeping reports to relevant functional heads for corrective action.
- Effluent and influent analysis and control and working with production function to minimize wastage by quantifying losses. The tests included BOD, COD, ph., Total solids, and total soluble solids and dissolved solids tests.
- Aflatoxin analysis in maize and its finished products like gluten feed, starch, gluten meal and maize germ.
- Sensory evaluation of finished products by coordinating a team of trained tasters to avert any off product getting to customer.
- Microbiological and sensory determination of portable water within the factory to avoid any cross contamination to the employees and the product.

#### **Shift Chemist**

March 2000 - March 2004

Corn Products Kenya Limited, Eldoret (Kenya)

### **Duties and Responsibilities**

- Performed routine chemical and physical tests that are raw materials, process intermediates and finished products to guide production on optimal operating limits and control of non- conforming products.
- Took part in both proficiency and repeatability tests
- Handled effluent analysis and control to avoid contamination.
- Internal equipment and chemical standardization for accuracy.
- Ensured proper record keeping and sample inventory management for traceability.
- Finished product packaging inspection to avoid cross contamination. This includes the drums, tankers and loading trucks.
- Company supplies pre-inspection and analysis.

### Food Technologist

### February 1999 - February 2000

Melvins Teas, Nairobi (Kenya)

### **Duties and Responsibilities**

In charge of production of spiced teas-ginger, vanilla and cinnamon. Product development

#### Attaché

February 1998 - April 1998

Mumias Sugar, (Kenya)

## **Duties and Responsibilities**

- Sampling regimes in sugar industry.
- Performance of analytical work of finished sucrose and its derivatives
- Agronomy tests including sugar analysis from field sugarcane varieties and soil analysis.

## **Notable Accomplishments**

- Steered my organization through successful ISO certification and recertification and transitions over the years which is key strategic tool.
- Put in place a robust risk management system with proper registers monitored by failure mode and effect analysis tool. This has drastically reduced organization exposure.
- I have pushed for green operation initiatives that include use of renewable energy through solar, water harvesting, plastic recycling, borehole water desalination, and tree planting as part of the sustainable initiatives.
- Increased customer satisfaction to current 83 % currently through structured feedback engagements and active complaints resolution mechanism.
- Development of SOPs and policies which guide operations thus increasing efficiency
- Awarded certificate of excellence in quality management by the World Confederation of businesses held in Malaysia November 2019(BIZZ awards).
- Managed between 95% to 100% score in proficiency and repeatability tests carried out in laboratory I was in charge. A clear pointer to accuracy of results and quality assurance.
- Part of innovation team that has pushed for process automation across processes and operations as part of lean management.

• Ensured an active employee safety system including safety teams, drills, trainings and safety barometer that has led to strong safety culture thus reducing accidents at work place.

## Skills & Specialization

ISO, complaints management, Auditing, Quality assurance, Quality control, SOPs, Process Improvement, CAPA, Regulatory compliance, Data analysis, Risk management, Training, strategic planning, budgeting

#### **Education**

**Kenyatta University** 

Jan 2015 - Jan 2017

MBA, Business Administration (Strategic Management)

**University of Eldoret** 

Jan 2010 - Jan 2013

Bachelor of Science, Food Science and Nutrition

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture (JKUAT)

Feb 1996 - Feb 1999

Diploma, Food Technology

Kakamega High School

Jan 1990 - Dec 1993

KCSE-B Minus.

Licenses, Certifications

**Lead Auditor** -ISO 22000:2018 **Nov 2019 - Present** 

Bureau Veritas

**Lead Auditor**-ISO 9001:2015 **Jun 2016 - Present** 

SGS

**Assessor**-ISO 17021-1-2015

KENAS April 2021 -Present

Page **6** of **7** 

### Referees

1. Mr. Samuel Charo

Finance Controller

Chai Trading Company Ltd

PO BOX 93324 MOMBASA

Cell phone: +254703744699.

E-Mail: scharo@chaitrading.com

2. Mr. Alfred Korir

Head of Finance.

Chai Trading Company Ltd

PO BOX 93324 MOMBASA

Cell phone: +254 773824845.

E-Mail: akorir@chaitrading.com

3. Mr. Gideon Mugo

Operations Director James Finlay Mombasa

E-Mail <u>Gideon.Mugo@jamesfinlay.co.ke</u>

Cell phone: +254722351154